Guide to the Eero Saarinen Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Project Records, 1936-1989; 1942-1962; Series IV
  - Job 5804: Dulles International Airport Terminal, Chantilly, VA
    The engineering firm Ammann and Whitney was hired by the U.S. government as the prime contractor for a second airport to serve Washington, D.C., which would be the first civilian airport built specially for jets. Ammann and Whitney hired Eero Saarinen and Associates to design its new two-level terminal and control tower. The undeveloped 9,800-acre site was to be reached via a new highway from the capital, twenty-three miles away. At 600 feet long by 150 feet wide, Saarinen's terminal was the nation's largest at the time it was built. The building's upper-level interior space, a single room free of columns housing waiting rooms and ticket counters, is enclosed by a steel-cable, tensioned roof suspended between rows of sixteen outward-curving concrete pylons. These supports are spaced 40 feet apart from each other, counteracting the cables' pull. Reinforced concrete was placed around the cables to stiffen them. Curving glass curtain walls are set between the pylons.
    Saarinen pioneered the concept of mobile lounges, which carry passengers from the concourse to their planes. On the landing-field side of the terminal, a wing containing a restaurant and observation deck leads to a fourteen-story control tower--a tapered concrete shaft topped by cantilevered control stations. Charles and Ray Eames created a film, "The Expanding Airport" (1958), to present the mobile lounge concept to the government; they also designed leather-and-aluminum Tandem Sling seating for the airport's interior. In the Saarinen office, the design team included Kent Cooper, David Jacob, Paul Kennon, Norman Pettula, Kevin Roche, and Warren Platner. In addition to its role as prime contractor, Ammann and Whitney acted as the associate architect/engineers of the terminal; Burns and McDonnell served as the mechanical engineers, and Dan Kiley was the landscape architect. The building was expanded in 1996.
    - Airport case studies, analysis and research
      - Airports, general, Circa 1960 (Box 460, Folder 1288)
        - Additional material (Box 703, Folder 223)
      - Airports reports summary, Circa 1960 (Box 460, Folder 1289)
      - Dallas, TX and South Bend, IN, Circa 1960 (Box 460, Folder 1290)
      - Friendship, Baltimore, MD, Circa 1960 (Box 460, Folder 1291)
      - Gatwick, London; other foreign airports, Circa 1960 (Box 460, Folder 1292)
      - Honolulu, Cleveland, Milwaukee, Wichita, Pittsburgh, Circa 1960 (Box 461, Folder 1293)
      - Idlewild and LaGuardia, NY, Circa 1960 (Box 461, Folder 1294)
      - Los Angeles and Monterey, CA, Circa 1960 (Box 461, Folder 1295)
      - O'Hare, Chicago, IL, Circa 1960 (Box 461, Folder 1296)
      - St. Louis, MO, Circa 1960 (Box 461, Folder 1297)
      - San Francisco, Philadelphia, PA, Circa 1960 (Box 461, Folder 1298)
      - Washington National Airport, DC, Circa 1960 (Box 461, Folder 1299)
      - Willow Run and Metropolitan airports; Central Railroad Terminal, Detroit, MI, Circa 1960 (Box 462, Folder 1300)
      - Washington D.C. and capital planning, general, 1958 (Box 462, Folder 1301)
    - Clippings, 1958-1965, 1973, 1982 (Box 462, Folder 1304 - 1305)
      - Additional material (Box 673, Folder 46)
    - Correspondence and memoranda
      - Concerning Charles Eames film, 1958-1959 (Box 462, Folder 1304)
      - Concerning press releases for airport and mobile lounge, 1958-1959 (Box 462, Folder 1305)
      - Interoffice memoranda, 1955-1965 (Box 462, Folder 1306)
      - Publicity and press, 1958-1964 (Box 463, Box 462, Folder 1309 - 1312)
    - Drawings
      - Apron buildings (FA-2898); inbound luggage (FA-3247); interior signs "as-built" sepias (FA-3217); miscellaneous title sheets; shop warehouse (FA-4003); west and feeder extensions, undated (Box 464)
      - Chair drawings and serving cart; design drawings; miscellaneous drawings, undated (Box 465)
      - Concessions and miscellaneous exterior sign layouts; sun problem, west kiosk: studies, charts; mobile lounge cab study, undated (Box 466)
      - Design drawings, undated (Box 467–469)
      - Detail sketches [from box 470], 1962 (Box 463, Folder 1311)
      - Exterior signs and miscellaneous drawings (FA-3178); sun control sketches "as-built" sepias, undated (Box 470)
      - Master plan
        - Originals and sepias; site plans and film, undated (Box 471)
        - Regulations A-G, undated (Box 472)
        - Report
          - Master Plan Report background material, undated (Box 473, Folder 1312)
          - Survey topographical maps [Mylars], Circa 1958 (Box 473, Folder 1313)
        - Master site plans 1965 and 1975; site plans - terminal area; site plans -stages, undated (Box 474)
        - Terminal design, undated (Box 475–477)
        - Terminal design; lighting and apron area -heliport and lamp post details, undated (Box 478)
      - Presentation plans and sections: schemes A, B, C; large scale plans and sections, undated (Box 482)
      - Renderings of interiors [watercolor], undated (Folder 691A)
      - Restaurant presentation drawings; furnishings drawings, undated (Box 483–484)
      - Shop warehouse & cargo buildings: yard work, electrical, structural, mechanical [sepias]; feeder line extensions [sepias], undated (Box 485)
      - Sketches, undated (Box 463, Folder 1314)
      - South finger studies and miscellaneous drawings; schedules, graphic program (Box 486)
      - Terminal building
        - Electrical sepias; electrical R-E sepias, undated (Box 487)
        - Finishes "as-built" sepias, undated (Box 488–490)
        - Mechanical sepias; RM sepias, undated (Box 491)
        - Structural sepias, undated (Box 492)
        - Structure "as-built" sepias, undated (Box 493)
      - Utility cluster [from box 466], 1963 (Box 463, Folder 1315)
      - Unidentified oversize drawing on board, undated (Box 479)
    - Graphics
      - Additional signage or sign changes, 1963-1964 (Box 463, Folder 1316)
      - Alphabet A for fascia [pieces], undated (Box 463, Folder 1317)
      - Alphabet AA [pieces], undated (Box 463, Folder 1318)
      - Alphabet B in various sizes, undated (Box 463, Folder 1319)
      - Alphabet C (for Solari), 1962 (Box 463, Folder 1320)
      - Car rental company logos and graphics, undated (Box 463, Folder 1321)
      - Correspondence regarding and drawings of reflector buttons for exterior signs, 1962 (Box 463, Folder 1322)
      - Dedication plaque correspondence, notes, samples, 1963 (Box 463, Folder 1323)
      - Door marking; dedication plaque location; location identifiers proof page, 1963 (Box 674, Folder 71)
      - Door signs specifications; room lists, 1963-1964, undated (Box 463, Folder 1324)
      - Expanded traffic letters and autopositive alphabet, undated (Box 463, Folder 1325)
      - Lower concourse doors for concessionaires, undated (Box 463, Folder 1326)
      - Office signs, undated (Box 678, Folder 118)
      - Presentation charts of ABCs, undated (Box 463, Folder 1327)
      - Proposed dispatchers' desks at deplaning areas, 1963 (Box 463, Folder 1328)
    - Interiors
      - Correspondence [includes fabric samples], 1962 (Box 463, Folder 1329)
      - Cost estimates; notes on prices, 1962 (Box 463, Folder 1330)
      - Manufacturers' brochures for restaurant furnishings, undated (Box 463, Folder 1331)
      - Specifications and finish schedules for terminal and Savarin Restaurants, 1962 (Box 463, Folder 1332)
    - Monthly progress reports, October 1960-March 1961 (Box 463, Folder 1335 - 1336)
    - Monthly progress reports, April 1961-January 1963 (Box 494, Folder 1337 - 1344)
    - Photographs
      - Aerial views of runways and terminal, Federal Aviation Agency, 1960, 1962 (Box 495, Folder 1343)
      - Construction, Circa 1961 (Box 495, Folder 1344)
        - Additional material (Box 673, Folder 47)
      - Curtain wall sill studies; construction; exteriors, Circa 1961 (Folder 686A, Folder 168)
      - Drawings of mobile lounge and terminal section at escalators, 1959, undated (Box 495, Folder 1345)
      - Exteriors, undated (Box 495, Folder 1346)
        - Additional material, part 1 (Box 673, Folder 47)
        - Additional material, part 2 (Box 676, Folder 93)
      - Floor plans; site plans, 1959, undated (Box 495, Folder 1347)
      - Interiors, undated (Box 495, Folder 1348)
      - Models, 1959, 1960, undated (Box 495, Folder 1349)
      - Negatives, undated (Box 495, Folder 1350)
      - Professional photographers
        - Cserna, George proof sheets: construction, Circa 1960 (Box 496, Folder 1351)
        - Hofer, Evelyn proof sheets: finished building, undated (Box 496, Folder 1352)
        - Korab, Baltazar
          - Proof sheets: construction, Circa 1960 (Box 496, Folder 1353)
          - Proof sheets: finished building, undated (Box 496, Folder 1354)
          - Proof sheets: model, undated (Box 496, Folder 1355)
          - Sample prints: finished building, undated (Box 496, Folder 1356)
        - Molitor, Joseph W. proof sheets: finished building, undated (Box 496, Folder 1357)
        - Page, Dan proof sheets: construction, Circa 1960 (Box 496, Folder 1358)
        - Stoller, Ezra proof sheets: finished building, undated (Box 496, Folder 1359)
      - Publicity binders
        - Models, renderings, plans, Circa 1960 (Box 496, Folder 1362 - 1363)
        - Presentation boards, images for boards, Circa 1958 (Box 496, Folder 1364 - 1365)
      - Renderings, 1960, undated (Box 496, Folder 1364)
      - Saarinen, Eero and others building model, undated (Folder 691C)
    - Presentation: "Our History" [boards for restaurant theme], undated (Folder 691B)
    - Press information
      - Dedication program and invitation to opening of Portals Restaurant, 1961-1962 (Box 497, Folder 1365)
      - "Dulles International Airport Fact Sheet", Federal Aviation Agency, Circa 1962 (Box 497, Folder 1366)
      - Federal Aviation Agency press kit information, 1959-1962 (Box 497, Folder 1367)
      - Press kit, Circa 1960 (Box 497, Folder 1368)
      - Press releases, 1958-1959 (Box 497, Folder 1369)
    - Program and government reports
      - Building development program for Washington International Airport, 1959 (Box 497, Folder 1370)
      - "First Annual Report, Federal Aviation Agency", 1959 (Box 497, Folder 1371)
      - Interim master plan [in part], 1959 (Box 497, Folder 1372)
      - Interim report on international and overseas air traffic and facilities requirements, 1959 (Box 497, Folder 1373)
      - "Master Development Plan Report for Dulles International Airport", 1960 (Box 497, Folder 1374)
      - "Master Plan Regulations, Dulles International Airport", undated (Folder 685A)
      - "Notes on the Interior Development of the Terminal Building, Dulles International Airport" typescript with illustrations, undated (Box 497, Folder 1375)
      - "Site Selection Study-Additional Airport for Washington, DC-Prepared for the White House", Greiner-Mattern, Associates [report], 1957 (Box 497, Folder 1376)
    - Publication: Gavinelli, Corrado. Projetti di Architettura Contemporanea: Eero Saarinen, il Terminal dell'Aeroporto Internazionale Dulles, 1984 (Box 497, Folder 1377)
    - Research files
      - Apron data, 1958 (Box 497, Folder 1378)
      - Air transport costs-"Air Transport Facts and Figures, 19th Edition, 1958", publication of the Air Transport Association of America (Box 497, Folder 1379)
      - Aircraft
        - Bristol Britannia, Circa 1958 (Box 497, Folder 1380)
        - Caravelle, Fairchild, Viscount, Circa 1958 (Box 498, Folder 1381)
        - Comet, Circa 1958 (Box 498, Folder 1382)
        - Convair, Circa 1958 (Box 498, Folder 1383)
        - Futuristic, Circa 1958 (Box 498, Folder 1384)
        - Lockheed, Circa 1958 (Box 498, Folder 1385)
      - Airport planning, Circa 1958 (Box 498, Folder 1388 - 1390)
      - Background information from Washington office, Circa 1958 (Box 499, Folder 1391 - 1392)
      - Miscellaneous aircraft images to scale, Circa 1960 (Box 499, Folder 1391)
      - Slides
        - Aerial views, 1959, undated (Box 499, Folder 1392)
        - Construction and details, 1962, 1963, undated (Box 499, Folder 1393)
        - Exteriors and interiors, 1963, undated (Box 499, Folder 1394)
        - Graphics, undated (Box 499, Folder 1395)
        - Master plan studies, 1958, undated (Box 499, Folder 1396)
        - Mobile lounge: design and production views, 1962, undated (Box 499, Folder 1397)
        - Models: exterior, 1959, undated (Box 499, Folder 1398)
        - Models: interior, 1962, undated (Box 499, Folder 1399)
        - Plans and sections, 1962, undated (Box 499, Folder 1400)
        - Presentation #1, undated (Box 499, Folder 1401)
        - Presentation #2, undated (Box 499, Folder 1402)
        - Research
          - Aircraft and mobile lounge: operation, circulation, parking, undated (Box 499, Folder 1403)
          - Airport bus in motion, undated (Box 499, Folder 1404)
          - Cargo handling, undated (Box 499, Folder 1405)
          - Finance, undated (Box 499, Folder 1406)
          - Interior space needs, 1958 (Box 499, Folder 1407)
          - Other airports, 1958, undated (Box 499, Folder 1408)
          - Passenger circulation and time-distance studies, undated (Box 499, Folder 1409)
          - Paving, utilities, drainage, undated (Box 499, Folder 1410)
    - Specifications
      - Aprons, taxiways and helistrip, 1962 (Box 500, Folder 1411)
      - Apron buildings and related utilities, 1962 (Box 500, Folder 1414 - 1415)
      - Aircraft aprons and utilities, 1959 (Box 500, Folder 1416 - 1418)
      - Access highway
        - Section I and east peripheral road, 1959 (Box 500, Folder 1417)
        - Section III, Circa 1960 (Box 500, Folder 1418)
        - Section IV, 1960 (Box 500, Folder 1419)
        - Section VI west peripheral road and Horsepen Dam, 1961 (Box 501, Folder 1420)
      - Built-in and loose furniture, and furnishing for Savarin Restaurants, 1962 (Box 501, Folder 1421)
      - Control tower, 1961 (Box 501, Folder 1422)
      - Display cases for Idlewild Pharmacy, Inc. newsstand concession, 1962 (Box 501, Folder 1423)
      - Exterior signs and public (loose) furnishings contract, 1962 (Box 501, Folder 1424)
      - Food and beverage facilities, Savarin Restaurants, 1962 (Box 501, Folder 1425)
      - Fuel concessionaire building, [1962] (Box 501, Folder 1428 - 1429)
      - Grading, paving, draining and utilities, 1958 (Box 501, Folder 1428)
      - Incoming baggage conveyors, 1961-1962 (Box 501, Folder 1429)
      - Landscape work, 1962 (Box 501, Folder 1430)
      - Maintenance lamp list, 1963 (Box 501, Folder 1431)
      - Miscellaneous utilities, 1962 (Box 502, Folder 1432)
      - Savarin Restaurant, [1962] (Box 502, Folder 1433)
      - Signage and pavement marking, 1962 (Box 502, Folder 1434)
      - Terminal building
        - Cabinet work, 1962 (Box 502, Folder 1435)
        - Finishes
          - Additional Terminal Building finishes, 1963 (Box 502, Folder 1436)
          - Amendments, 1961 (Box 502, Folder 1437)
          - Bulletins #1 - #22 [missing #6, #14, #15, #20], 1961-1962 (Box 502, Folder 1438)
          - Finishing, utility and miscellaneous work, 1961 (Box 502, Folder 1441 - 1442)
        - Signs, 1962 (Box 503, Folder 1441)
        - Structure bulletins [missing #1, #3, #10, #19, #40, #48, #51], 1960-1962 (Box 503, Folder 1442)
        - Structural work, 1960 (Box 503, Folder 1443)
      - Terminal yardwork, 1961 (Box 503, Folder 1446 - 1447)
      - Utilities buildings and installations, 1960 (Box 503, Folder 1448 - 1449)
      - West building group, 1961-1962 (Box 503, Folder 1450 - 1451, Box 504)
  - Job 5805: Yale University, New Haven, CT: New Colleges [Samuel F. B. Morse and Ezra Stiles Colleges]
    To accommodate 250 students in each of two residential colleges on the northwest edge of the Yale University campus, Eero Saarinen and Associates formed courtyards defined with low-rise polygonal buildings punctuated by two high-rise towers. The colleges are separated by an open pedestrian walk leading to the massively scaled neo-Gothic Payne Whitney Gymnasium, which together with the colleges' curving building wall form a plaza. The colleges' varied silhouette results less from programmatic requirement than design intuition; during the design process, Saarinen reputedly used balloons raised to different heights to help envision the building profile.
    Because the colleges' budget precluded the use of traditional masonry, which had been employed for Yale's older dormitories, Saarinen pioneered a method of concrete construction, aiming to produce what he described as "masonry walls made without masons." The Prepakt Concrete Company of Cleveland, Ohio, which had been identified by John Dinkeloo, built walls through which concrete was poured to surround rough-cut stones three to eight inches in length. Abstract freestanding and relief sculptures by Costantino Nivola were placed throughout the complex. Pedestrian pathways weaving through the residential colleges incorporate changes in grade and offer varied and changing vistas.
    Inside, the buildings' complex footprints result in irregularly shaped rooms that Saarinen hoped would be "as individual as possible, as random as those in an old inn."
    - Clippings, 1959-1965, undated (Box 504, Folder 1450)
      - Additional material (Box 673, Folder 48)
    - Correspondence: publicity and press, 1959-1962 (Box 504, Folder 1453 - 1454)
    - Drawings
      - Architectural mylars, undated (Box 505–506)
      - Architectural mylars; kitchen, undated (Box 507)
      - Architectual mylars; sprinkler layout; heating and air conditioning; electrical, undated (Box 508)
      - Cornerstone, undated (Box 541)
      - Design drawings, undated (Box 509–510)
      - Furnishings, undated (Box 511)
      - Miscellaneous oversize plans and sections, undated (Box 512–539)
      - Site plans; floor plans, 1960 (Folder 693A–693D)
      - Site plantings, lighting sepias; sketches - renderings, undated (Box 540)
      - Sketches, undated (Box 541)
      - Site plan - rendering, undated (Box 540A)
        Conditions Governing Access
        The site plan in Box 540A is restricted for conservation reasons. Researchers must use a digital surrogate.
    - Graphics
      - Door signs studies, notes, correspondence, 1962, undated (Box 504, Folder 1453)
      - Ezra Stiles Master's House sign, undated (Box 674, Folder 72)
      - Room number mock-ups and samples, undated (Box 504, Folder 1454)
        - Additional material (Box 673, Folder 49)
    - Interiors
      - Correspondence; memoranda; conference notes; manufacturers' brochures; drawings, 1962 (Box 504, Folder 1455)
      - Furnishings specifications; furniture cost estimates; furniture lists; lamps schedule, 1962 (Box 504, Folder 1456)
      - Materials samples, 1959-1962 (Box 504, Folder 1457)
      - Materials samples, 1959-1962 (Box 542, Folder 1458)
    - Photographs
      - Construction photographs 1:1 -25:4, 1960-1962 (Box 542, Folder 1461 - 1462)
      - Construction site, undated (Box 542, Folder 1461)
      - Early model progress, 1959 (Box 542, Folder 1462)
      - Exteriors, undated (Box 543, Folder 1463)
        - Additional material (Box 673, Folder 50)
      - Interior details, Stiles, 1967 (Box 674, Folder 73)
      - Interiors, Undated, 1967 (Box 543, Folder 1464)
        - Additional material (Box 673, Folder 50)
      - Models, 1958-1960 (Box 543, Folder 1465)
        - Additional material (Box 673, Folder 50)
      - Negatives and transparencies, 1959, undated (Box 543, Folder 1466)
      - Nivola, Constantino and work samples, undated (Box 543, Folder 1467)
      - Pre-existing site and surroundings, undated (Box 543, Folder 1468)
      - Professional photographers
        - Clark, Joe proof sheets, undated (Box 543, Folder 1469)
        - Cserna, George proof sheets, undated (Box 543, Folder 1470)
        - Korab, Baltazar proof sheets, undated (Box 543, Folder 1471)
      - Renderings and sketches, 1959, undated (Box 543, Folder 1472)
      - Site plans; floor plans, 1959, undated (Box 543, Folder 1473)
        - Additional material (Box 676, Folder 94)
      - Stone walls, 1959-1960, undated (Box 543, Folder 1474)
    - Specifications
      - Addenda, 1960 (Box 543, Folder 1475)
      - Bulletins #1 - #54, 1960-1962 (Box 543, Folder 1478 - 1481, Box 544)
      - General contract, architectural, elevators and dumbwaiters, mechanical, electrical, food service, 1960 (Box 544, Folder 1482 - 1483)
      - Inspection service contract, 1960 (Box 544, Folder 1482)
      - Landscaping, 1962 (Box 544, Folder 1483)
      - Test borings, 1959 (Box 544, Folder 1484)
    - University publications, 1956, 1959, 1962 (Box 544, Folder 1485)
  - Job 5807: Lincoln Center: Vivian Beaumont Repertory Theater and Library Museum
    In 1956, John D. Rockefeller III, who was president of the newly formed Lincoln Center, Inc., and responsible for overseeing the design and construction of the cultural arts complex in Manhattan, received a preliminary list of international architects recommended by Wallace K. Harrison, but the center's board of trustees insisted that only American architects participate. Two years later, with all of the architects still not chosen, Harrison suggested that Eero Saarinen design the center's repertory theater. Gordon Bunshaft, partner and chief designer at Skidmore, Owings, and Merrill, was selected to design an adjacent structure housing a library and museum. Saarinen designed the Beaumont Theater in collaboration with his associate Cesar Pelli and the theater designer Jo Mielziner; Ammann and Whitney acted as the project's structural engineers, and Syska and Hennessy its mechanical engineers.
    Responding to the site, which faced a plaza containing a 125-foot-by-80-foot reflecting pool with a bronze sculpture by Henry Moore, the architects joined forces to design a single building. The building features a sunken lobby leading to the theater's main level, and a cantilevered walkway opening onto the loge. In addition to its principal performing space, the Beaumont contains a 299-seat amphitheater-style theater, initially called the Forum and later known as the Mitzi Newhouse Theater, located below the main theater's entrance level.
    - Clippings, 1965-1966 (Box 544, Folder 1486)
    - Correspondence
      - Belluschi, Pietro, 1956, 1958 (Box 544, Folder 1487)
      - Publicity and press, 1959-1962 (Box 544, Folder 1488)
    - Drawings
      - Architectural "as-built" tracings, undated (Box 545–546)
      - Design drawing revisions, 2 June 1961; 19 June 1961 (Box 547)
      - Electrical mylars, undated (Box 548)
      - Exterior rendering [watercolor], undated (Folder 686B, Folder 169)
      - Fishbach & Moore record drawings [prints], undated (Box 549–550)
      - Furniture "as-built" tracings; SKA drawings, undated (Box 551)
      - Heating tracings, undated (Box 552)
      - North Plaza studies, undated (Box 553)
      - Original design sketches; reference materials, undated (Box 554)
      - Plumbing, undated (Box 555)
      - Seating and furniture (not in "as-built" set), undated (Box 556)
      - Signs (not in "as-built" set) and seating, undated (Box 557)
      - Sketches, undated (Box 544, Folder 1489)
        - Additional material (Box 682, Folder 142-144)
      - Sketches; rendering; seating plans; sections; elevations, 1960, undated (Box 678, Folder 119)
      - Sprinkers "as-built"; Fishbach & Moore prints - "as-built" electrical - revision 1, undated (Box 558)
      - Temporary repertory theater mylars and sepias (Job #5807-X-1), undated (Box 559)
    - Graphics: Sign schedule and color samples, 1965, undated (Box 544, Folder 1490)
    - Interiors